<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "1.dtd">

<rfc>
    <front>
        <title abbrev="workflow of projects">
            Proposed workflow for Scientific and Learning Projects carried out as a Group
        </title>
        <author initials="K.D." surname="Sinkar" fullname="Koustubh D. Sinkar">
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <city>Pune</city>
                    <region>Maharashtra</region>
                    <country>India</country>
                </postal>
                <email>ksinkar@gmail.com</email>
                <uri>http://www.ksinkar.in</uri>
            </address>
        </author>
        <date month="April" year="2012"></date>
        <area>Experimental</area>
        <workgroup>Ethics Working Group</workgroup>
        <keyword>workflow</keyword>
        <keyword>projects</keyword>
        <keyword>hackerspace</keyword>
        <keyword>doothings</keyword>
        <abstract>
            <t> This memo presents a workflow for doing scientific projects in a
            group, especially of the technical nature related to programming,
            computer science and electrical engineering but NOT limited to those
            fields. The workflow also applies to the learning of complex knowledge
            with the help of peer groups, especially in the absence of a
            structured environment for learning without a trained instructor
            as is provided in Universities and Colleges.
            </t>
        </abstract>
    </front>
    <middle>
        <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
            <t> At various hackerspaces in and around Pune various projects are
            being attempted. The number of hackerspaces abound and so do the
            number of projects. Unfortunately all of the projects that are being
            attempted at various hackerspaces are usually of the beginner level
            and only some of them graduate to intermediate or to the advanced
            level.
            </t>
            <t> This is a proposed framework to carry out projects and to learn
            complex skill sets in a self-learning group such that at the end of
            the project the participant has retained majority of the knowledge
            and is capable of attempting the same tasks with more confidence
            and in less amount of time (the participant having successfully
            climbed the learning curve in the previous iteration).
            </t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="project" title="The Project and its types">
            <t> A project is nothing but a group of doable tasks with specific
            objectives each, a time constraint for performing each task and
            a specific structure about how to go about attempting all the tasks.
            </t>
            <section anchor="project_classification" title="Classification">
                Any project that is attempted can be classified into one of the
                following types:-
                <list style="symbols">
                    <t>Learning</t>
                    <t>Building</t>
                </list>
            </section>
            A project that is going to be attempted should have the following
            ingredients:-
            <list>
                <t> A well defined list of tasks with an objective each</t>
                <t> The number of meetings to attempt that project should
                not be more than five. If it seems that the number of meetings
                for the given project are going to be more than 5 then reconsider
                splitting the project into two projects.
                </t>
                <t> A project is headed by a project master. The project master
                is the leader of the project
                </t>
            </list>
        </section>
        <section anchor="group_composition" title="Group Composition">
            <t>Whenever we are working in a group there is always a slight
            management/co-ordination overhead just because of the fact that it
            is a group activity. All the members of the group that are
            participating in the project are going to be equal participants in
            the project as far as the activities of learning and building are
            concerned. But in spite of that there will be participants who are
            willing to take more initiative and go the extra mile to help the
            project succeed. These participants  will have to volunteer to take
            care of these meta tasks. These participants shall form the Enablers
            Team. The other participants will merely participate in the project
            helping achieve the project objectives.
            </t>
            <section anchor="participants" title="The Participants">
                <t> The participants in the project should be individuals who
                are sufficiently motivated and interested in the objectives of
                the project and have the pre-requisite abilities to finish the
                tasks in the project. The number of participants in the project
                should not be more than 25 people not including the Enablers.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="enablers" title="The Enablers">
                <t>  The Enablers' team will ideate, originate and enable the
                project. While working in a team it is best when the responsibilities
                of each individual are clearly defined as it helps in better
                execution and less interference from other members of the team.
                The Enablers team consists of the following members:
                <list style="numbers">
                    <t> The Project Master</t>
                    <t> Subject Matter Expert/s </t>
                    <t> The Sergeant at Arms </t>
                    <t> The Human Link </t>
                    <t> The Treasurer </t>
                </list>
                </t>
                <section anchor="project_master" title="The Project Master">
                    <t> A project is headed by a Project Master (PM). The PM is
                    the chief enabler of the project. He/she is not necessarily the most
                    scientifically/technically competent participant in the project, but
                    it is his responsibility as the creator of the project to clearly
                    lay down the objectives of the project and determine its overall
                    structure. It is the PM's responsibility to build the
                    Enablers' Team to assist him in successfully enabling the
                    project. The other role-players should be competent and
                    motivated enough to discharge their duties. If under any
                    circumstances they are unable to do so, the PM has to step in
                    and discharge their duties in addition to his existing ones. It is
                    also his responsibility to involve the subject matter expert/s
                    while creating the structure of the project.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="subject_matter_expert" title="Subject Matter Expert/s">
                    <t> A Subject Matter Expert (SME) is someone who has done work which
                    is similar/related to the work being done in the current project.
                    He/she should be reasonably be more confident about the
                    subject than the rest of the participants. He/she should have
                    a fair and reasonable idea as to challenges that will be faced
                    in the course of the project. He/she shall be primarily responsible
                    for the structure of the project and its planning. During the
                    project his role will be that of a mentor. If the SME
                    is himself/herself a novice, then it is his/her duty to
                    prepare reasonably well in advance and be prepared to
                    help/guide others during the project meetings.
                    </t>
                    <t> There can be more than one Subject Matter Experts
                    for a project. More than one Subject Matter Experts maybe
                    required for an extremely complex project, but most of the
                    intermediate level and even the advanced projects need only
                    one subject matter expert. Having more than subject matter
                    expert/s when not required will not lighten the burden instead
                    it will create more confusion and stale-mates within the
                    Project Team.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="saa" title="The Sergeant-at-Arms">
                    <t> The Sergeant at Arms (SAA) is responsible for the infrastructure
                    and logistics of the project in question. He/she has to make
                    sure that the necessary permissions for carrying out the
                    project at the venue have been acquired and the apparatus
                    needed for doing the project is ready for use and well-tested.
                    It is expected of the SAA within reasonable limits to have
                    alternative backups in place if the primary apparatus fails.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="human_link" title="The Human Link">
                    <t>The Human Link (HL) is responsible for making sure that
                    an interested audience is aware of the project taking place.
                    He/she has to make sure that the project participants are on
                    the same page about project meeting venue and timings. The
                    HL is primarily responsible for communication between the
                    Enablers and rest of the Participants.
                    </t>
                </section>
                <section anchor="treasurer" title="The Treasurer">
                    <t> The Treasurer is responsible for the finance management
                    of the project if any. Some projects might not need a
                    treasurer at all in case if no money is involved. But a
                    person separate than the SAA is recommended for handling
                    the finances of the project if they are significant.
                    </t>
                </section>

                <t> There is no hard and fast rule that each of the roles defined
                above have to be done by separate individuals. It is perfectly
                okay for one individual to perform multiple roles or to perform
                all these roles, but it is better and recommended that the
                responsibilities are divided to avoid a burnout and to keep
                process of doing these projects from dying out. Also the
                involvement of multiple individuals in the process makes sure
                that a community feeling is fostered and the process continues
                to live even if individuals leave the community. The reason why
                this process has been proposed is to stop the decline that
                that community faces once the individuals who led it have to
                leave it.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>
    </middle>
    <back>
    </back>
</rfc>
